<article>
  <meta>
    <title>ArticleML: A Markup Language For Writing Math-y Articles For The Web</title>
    <author>Zach Flynn</author>
    <date>today</date>
  </meta>

  <section name="Why ArticleML?">
    <p>
      ArticleML is a markup language for writing research articles for the web.  Its goal is to give researchers the main capabilities of LaTex (and beyond!) on the internet so more articles are written in HTML instead of PDF.
    </p>

    <p>
      Research articles are generally written in LaTex (or using Word Processors) and output to PDF.  PDF is a print-based solution and documents written in this way look great on paper.  But most academic and industry research is no longer consumed via printouts but on the web, where PDF is a poor, non-native format.  For example, it is impossible to link directly to a certain section of the article if you are discussing it.  With a hypertext like HTML, this is easy to do.
    </p>

    <p>
      HTML documents also makes research more accessible since screen readers and the like will work with normal HTML documents because the text is available in the document.
    </p>

    <p>
      Articles rarely only get distributed when they appear in journals.  Usually they appear in draft form on the authors' websites long before publication.  HTML research articles allow the draft to be easily embedded into an author's website and make the document easier to quote from or cite in online discussions about the research.
    </p>

    <p>
      HTML is a parseable, searchable format (especially the HTML output by ArticleML which is valid XML) while the PDF format requires sophisticated parsing to access relevant information in an article programmatically.
    </p>

    <p>
      For all these reasons, academic research output would be better delivered in HTML than in PDF.  ArticleML provides a simple markup format that makes this easy to do while still giving researchers the niceties they've come to expect from systems like LaTex (citation management, reference links to other sections, etc).
    </p>
  </section>

  <section name="Why XML?">
    <p>I considered adding the math language used in ArticleML to say a lightweight markup language like Markdown, but decided that it could not solve the problem because such languages contain <i>formatting</i> info but not <i>semantic</i> info which is necessary to truly replace something like LaTex.  ArticleML documents can naturally have attributes like: authors, titles, sections, etc, because it uses XML as the base language.</p>
  </section>

  

  

</article>
